Hi everyone, I'm executive editor Steve Ehrlich and I'm here today with Willam Bauter.
Willam is a longtime practitioner in the financial space.
He was a member of the UK's NPC, which is basically the equivalent of the FOMC here.
He's a former chief economist at Citi and has had a long distinguished history career
in the financial industry.
So welcome, Willam.
Thank you.
It's a pleasure.
Let's get right into it.
You run not bad in the financial times a couple of weeks ago.
They really kind of caught my eye and basically the gist of it was that central banks should
quote unquote get out of the gold game.
You started it by pointing out, I guess, your belief that gold is in what you call it that
believe a 6,000 year bubble and I think that's a great place to start.
Can you just explain what you meant by that?
Gold is valued mostly for the belief that it is a good store of value.
It has very few intrinsic services that it yields either as a consumption good.
Yes, I can hang jewelry around my neck, but much of it jewelry even is viewed as an investment
rather than something done for its beauty itself.
And of course, there's some uses in dentistry, some advanced technology that may make use
of gold, but it basically has very little intrinsic value.
So this $4,000 plus value that we see today is that high simply because people believe
it will be a valuable store for a value.
And this belief is self-fulfilling and incredibly fragile, it's damaged like Bitcoin.
Bitcoin actually has a proper use as a means of payment, often for illegal transactions,
of course, but that makes a desirable goal used to be back in the middle ages and before
3,000 GSBC viewed as a means of payment therefore store of value, but nobody really these days
exchanges gold that they go to the shop.
So gold value is for people think it will be.
And that is incredibly fragile support for the value of that intrinsically very low value
commodity.
And no central bank should simply because historically we've had the gold standard.
And the Mesopotamians use gold as a store of value means of payment.
You don't want to be a slave of history, yet alternative superior means of payments
and store of values and central banks should hold their assets in a diversified portfolio
of a real and financial instruments.
And to the US has more than eight metric tons the US government in gold reserves, worth
at current market prices over a trillion, this is completely insane.
It's a very risky bet they should get rid of the gold, shell it to people that can afford
to lose the value that they buy.
And you don't want to sell it to people who are financially fragile, but don't just sell
it to the speculators who believe you'll go up and can survive financially if it doesn't.
And you invest the trillion in diversified portfolio of financial real assets, it protects
the taxpayer.
Okay, so a few things to unpack there, I know some of the crypto people listening here will
love one of the things that you said and will strongly disagree with one of the things that
I'll begin with the latter, the statement that most Bitcoin payments are used for illicit
purposes.
We could have an entire other conversation, I've had plenty with data pushing back on
that statement.
That's not what we're going to do here though.
But the idea that Bitcoin has more intrinsic value than gold.
I know the industry will love.
But let's just unpack what you said a little bit more here.
I mean, gold is in a 6,000 year bubble and in a way, that sometimes could almost seem
like a Nazi moron a bit to me because bubbles just don't last that long.
I mean, there may be boom and bust cycles over the years, I mean like tulip bulbs, the
South Sea, railroads in the US, the list goes on and on and on.
Gold though keeps going up through millennia and how does that square with your, it might
only be worth what people want to pay.
Gold has been a very risky commodity in the past.
Remember, remember we had the gold standards in this 30s, 40s and all that.
Gold was the price is $35 to finance.
And before we got the gold standard, gold prices in this 16, 70s, 10s, you were significantly
higher than that.
So bubbles can last forever.
They have ups and they have downs.
And so gold, gold, gold, gold, gold, gold as a bubble for nearly 6,000 years.
But Jay, willingness of people to hold something simply because they believe many other people
are holding central banks and build, if you would, as a valuable investment instrument,
reliable store of value is very much upside and very little downside.
No, that doesn't make no sense.
So let's get to it then, let's say the US sells its trillions in gold.
What should they buy?
You said it diversified portfolio, I guess, various stocks and commodities.
Would they just purchase diversified index funds?
Is there a case to put some Bitcoin on the central bank balance sheet?
I myself consider Bitcoin to be extremely risky investment.
I don't think that even in the diversified portfolio, central banks should invest in it.
Central banks can afford the loss if it's the price of Bitcoin to go to zero even.
But this is not something that I think should be part of a wealth structure portfolio.
The portfolio of the central bank could include exchange traded funds, holding commodities,
stocks, shares, and other financial insurance.
So it should just be diversified without any crazy exposures, like gold and Bitcoin.
Let's just talk a little more about the world we live in today.
The basement trade is sort of all the rage.
I mean, the US dollar, I think, is down 11% or so far this year.
It's had one of its worst big starts for a year in decades.
There's easing pressure all across the UK, Eurozone, and in some circles, there is a
fear that we might be seeing a transition away from the dollarized economy.
In this period of inflation, that's why people are running to gold.
Where do you see the current cycle with relation to gold and with central banks continuing
to acquire it, should they sell it right away?
Is there more room to run before they do so?
What is interesting about this debasement, the game, is that in the past, doubts about
the security of the dollar let you fly into other currencies, the euro, sterling, the
end.
Now, of course, the remainder you want, but this particular depreciation of the dollar
has been not quite matched, but has been not that much larger than the weakening of other
leading currencies.
People have doubts about the yield of the credit worthiness or the inflationary debasement
that will come in countries, this unsustainable fiscal situation.
The US is volatile, but so is the UK, so is Japan, so are most advanced economies.
Even China, when you add in local government and all that, has potentially material public
debt challenge which could lead to inflation in some cases, then the US, if Congress were
to fail to raise that ceiling entirely, you would even have a technical default, so you
want to be out of that.
So the slight into gold is really a good buy to all leading currencies, and the reserve
state of the dollar is threatened by so-called reserve status of most other rival currencies.
But I hope and I expect that some fiscal adjustment, fiscal consolidation bill in lots of distance
to begin in all countries that need this badly, and so while I think an inflationary outcome
is definitely at risk for the US, for the euro, for the UK, for Japan, I think it is
probably a very materialized, I wouldn't want to be in gold, I would want to be diversified
portfolio of real assets, or in that linked instrument for that matter, it's the only
serious inflation, which of course you can't cover in this indexing instrument, and not
default, which of course would affect indexing the instrument as well.
So even if you are convinced that the dollar will shrink in significance as a reserve currency
and as a means of payment for cross-border transactions, there's still the alternative
investment will be diversified portfolio of real assets, not a single highly risky commodity.
And when you say real assets, I mean you're talking about stocks, I mean companies that
earn revenues and then also certain commodities as well, you have commodities in ETF of wide
range of commodities, including if they were to be traded, it seems on rare earth.
I'm sure there's somebody working on that.
We need to take a very quick break to hear from one of our sponsors and then we're going
to be right back and talk some more.
Binance is the world's number one crypto exchange, trusted by over 290 million users.
With industry leading liquidity, security and a wide range of digital asset products,
Binance is the place to buy, sell, trade and earn crypto.
Download Binance today to get started.
All right, so one of the things I appreciated about the article and our discussions even
before this interview is your openness to Bitcoin and the understanding that it's meant
to be a payment system.
I want to get your thoughts on how that dovetails in a way that is actually used today though.
Obviously, it was created to be a peer-to-peer payment system decentralized outside of the,
I guess, the reach of any real government.
But as I'm sure you're well aware, today the mantra is total, hold on for dear life.
Michael Saylor, the personality behind strategy, frequently says, "Don't sell your Bitcoin
under any circumstances and with supply of the emissions rates continuing to drop, the
actual velocity of Bitcoin is falling."
What is your sense of that and then what might need to happen for Bitcoin, regardless of
whether or not it goes on a central bank balance sheet, to become a having more of an economy
behind it.
Either talking about just payments or an emerging trend of what we call BTC or decentralized
finance involving Bitcoin.
I don't think that Bitcoin as a private fiduciary digital instrument without anything
backing it, other than to believe that it has value, is desirable store of value or means
of payment.
It's way too volatile.
So I'm a great believer in the future of blockchain-based payment instruments, stable
coins, but they have to be sorry backed by either central bank reserves or by claims
on short duration strategy debt.
And so Bitcoin simply doesn't meet this criteria.
There's also, of course, the point which I think will never get mentioned, but that
while Bitcoin, the total stock is limited at 20 million units, that's why the issuance
goes down, there is no reason why we could not simply introduce Bitcoin to exactly the
same program or Bitcoin 3, 4, 5, 6, and 7.
And if people believe that a new Bitcoin is as good as your Bitcoin, then it will be
a massive increase in the aggregate stock of many Bitcoins.
So the fact that Bitcoin is capped doesn't mean that you cannot create basically identical
financial instruments.
Well, one thing I would say to that effect is that there must be tens, hundreds, thousands
of Bitcoin clones, Bitcoin derivatives, because all the code as you mentioned is open source.
It's freely available.
I could create Steve Coin that has the same emissions schedule.
You could create Willem Coin.
But the sort of community surrounding Bitcoin and the hash rate, the computing power that
helps secure the network, all of that has proven to be an insurmountable sort of moat
against any potential copycats from trying to sort of steal my share directly away from
Bitcoin.
So I've heard that retort that you've mentioned that people could just create more despite
this hardcat limit.
But for what it's worth, it really appears that everyone, governments, companies, individuals,
they agree that there is a Bitcoin and then there are other Bitcoin type products that
might try to go after a different use case.
But those are not seen as substitutes in the minds of most...
They are not seen as substitutes, because they are not seen as substitutes.
If they were seen as substitutes, they would be.
So these things are, again, totally mindset-driven valuations.
There's nothing intrinsic in Bitcoin that makes it unique or irreducible.
But at some point, maybe not for a century, somebody will go, "People think, 'Why not?'
And do why not good directly affect the valuation of Bitcoin?"
But I think not limit this discussion to Bitcoin, we really think that stable coins are likely
properly backed to be different in the future, and the authority to be able to finally agree
to interest being paid on stable coins fully back.
Yeah, I agree.
And that's the next place I want to take the discussion, because I know one of the things
I found really interesting when we spoke last week is that in the UK, I think there are
movements that try to limit the amount of stable coins that people can hold.
I know lobbyists in the United States, on behalf of banks, are trying to limit stable
coins usage because of fears of the...
Excuse me, because it will suck deposits and then potentially credit out of the banking
system.
And you pretty forcefully pushed back and said that was ridiculous.
So maybe you could just expand on that.
There's no doubt that those designed stable coins, fully back to arms, paying interest
would be competitive with bank deposits.
I actually would require bank deposits to be fully backed by central bank reserves or
short-waste churches as well.
Of course, they're not.
They have this fractional reserve banking.
But let's think that the rate it would be to reintroduce the stable coins, the technological
superior to bank deposits, and people switch to them.
Banks lose deposits.
That interferes with financial intermediation, yes, but it doesn't have to because assume
the stable coin now is fully backed by central bank deposits, central bank has to do something
with these additional reserves as they're issuing.
It can simply put the money as long-term investments back in the bank.
So they can go with the intermediation between private agents.
They simply take the monetary function out of the banking system and unless the banks
were to create certain release, legally distinct, which just issued stable coins, fully backed
by central bank reserves assured duration treasury.
So there's absolutely no fear of financial chaos, even if stable coins were to cause
the complete departure of bank deposits from the bank's balance sheet.
The central bank development can always put it back into banks if they think that intermediation
through the banking sector remains important.
One of the questions I really wanted to ask you, and it kind of extends from what you just
spoke about.
There's been a few different ways of creating a blockchain-based currency, and you've mentioned
each of them.
One that's traditionally fully reserved, one-to-one stable coin either backed by a dollar
in a commercial bank, although I guess technically if those dollars are about to cater to maybe
it's not, then there are tokenized deposits which are not fully one-to-one backed.
This is interesting, in fact, because our former employer, I work with the city for about
a year as well, Jane Brady, the current CEO, cities experimenting right now with stable
coins while Jane Fraser actually said, I think last week, that she thinks tokenized deposits
are a better way to go.
JP Morgan's also experimenting with tokenized deposits on blockchain-based by Coinbase, and
then you mentioned central bank digital currencies.
As I'm sure you know, those have fallen into disrepute, especially here in the United States,
where there's even talk of bills banning the idea of a central bank digital currency because
it fears over privacy.
Maybe you could just...
I'd love to get your thoughts on just those three different categories.
One of the pros and cons of each, and then I want to get into privately-issued stable
coins potentially paying interest because that's a very hot topic of discussion in the United
States now.
Yeah, tokenized deposits are basically partially backed stable coins, right?
They're on the blockchain, but they just treat it from a reserve backing requirement
as central bank... as commercial bank deposits.
I consider that desirable because in the partial backing of bank deposits today and tokenized
bank deposits in the future means there's always a risk for bank runs, so we have to
have the deposit insurance that we have to have the central bank to stand ready to act
as a lender of ours, these two major and I would say financially unfair sources of support
for financial support for the banks that are matched by title regulations to make sure
that banks don't go crazy because the deposits are insured and the landlords are there.
So, we can do a way with both deposit insurance and there's a need for the central bank to
act as a lender of ours for short, in the case of bank runs, and with the restrictive
and costly regulations of banks that are the other side of the equation and simply have
fully backed bank deposits on the blockchain, possibly in a legally distinct unit to the
bank, and that means they would be stable coins, partially backed stable coins are
simply a way to be covered by post-insurance, and lenders of ours are certainly a way of
giving a financial edge to the banks at a cost utterly borne by the taxpayer, so it's
undesirable.
And CVDC, central bank digital currency, I think is desirable, but one reason is that
if you make them not easily available on chain and off chain to a CVDC card that you can
waive and make payments with, so retail availability on, as I said, on chain and off chain, and
you also know restrictions on the size of the account or the transactions, and you allow
them to pay interest, but they will be superior to coin currency, which could be abolished,
which would have the advantage of eliminating the lower-bound non-industry.
Central banks cannot set inter-stage meaning from below zero, because the zero inter-state
of currency or paper currency effectively sets the floor, and so following the great financial
crisis in the themes of this and following the COVID crisis, they should have been able
of the central bank to set the interest rate, the bank rate at minus three or minus four
percent.
Couldn't do that.
So there are two crazy things, like expanding the balance sheet by trillions encourages financial
access and speculation.
So I think CVDC's are an excellent idea that you require doing away with currencies, and
that means the currency goes away, but you couldn't have floor privacy as CVDC's, but
you could have the synonymity, that you could have the wallets holding the CVDC being covered
by appropriate crypto protections.
So you could still chase, of course, transactions, unless you get into Bitcoin, but you don't
know who is the beneficiary owner of the wallets it holds.
And I've spoken with Congressmen and lawmakers more on the Democratic side, because it must
be universal Republican opposition to the CVDC at this point in the US, where they espouse
a lot of the same arguments that you just made.
And sometimes I study privacy law prior life of mine, and I always laugh at how surveilled
our financial system is already just by private banks that have to work with the government
anyway.
So the idea that CVDC is going to introduce this Orwellian dystopian society, I think
sometimes people need to realize how we're already living so far, and truly cash is,
I guess, the only real anonymous way of making payments.
But yeah, I understand that.
One question I do want to ask, there's a growing number of companies here in the US
who are trying to get Fedmaster accounts, so they can interact directly with the central
bank and not have their intermediaries.
No one has been successful in getting one yet.
A couple of people have gotten like federal trust charters, but that's more for just
paying, not taking deposits.
And a Fed governor actually, I think last week, suggests an idea of a type of Fedmaster
Lite account to sort of not give full access to some of these crypto companies that like
a JP Morgan or Wells Fargo gets, but let them help this intermediate themselves a little
bit.
What are your thoughts on crypto, let's say stable coin issuers directly interacting
with central banks, be it the Fed or perhaps even the Bank of England?
No, that's exactly what I mean by having a CVDC that you, at all, and any corporation
can have an account with the central bank, with the Fed saying this, or with a lot of
central banks, yes, that CVDC is simply a stable coin issue by the central bank, right?
So I think it's desirable.
It's part of the veto CVDC.
The whole fair includes commercial banks themselves, they of course haven't already, but I would
expound this to any legitimate, well, for the first instance, it's a domestic resident,
but there's no reason in principle why foreign entities should not be able to have an account
with the central bank, yes, that would of course compete with this private stable coins and
which one they would use, would depend on which one pays the better interest rate and
which one is more efficient.
I believe that progress in the speed, reliability of payments is likely to be greater in the
private sector in the central bank.
So I think stable coins issued private entities should still be able to compete with CVDC,
which is available retail and wholesale.
What do you make of sort of like the growing trend?
I mean, now that the genius act has passed here in the U.S. all to sort of set the rules
for privately issued stable coins, I mean, there's circle, there's tether, there's some
sort of algorithm because of our term, but there's like things like Athena, but now we're
talking about the banks and some of the big box retailers, like the Amazon's, the Walmart's,
they're kicking tires under unstable coins.
How many stable coins do you think the world can support at scale and like, how do you
think wins?
Do you think it's going to be a more neutral party whose only business is a stable coin
like a circle or a tether or is it a world where JP Morgan comes in and launches JPM
coin and just dwarfs all of them or is it going to be incumbent upon the banks to kind
of work together and create like a consortium where they have one stable coin that is fungible
across all of their different entities?
Well, stable coins are fungible as if the issue is, right, at the moment, we can transact
maybe between persons having accounts with different banks, but there's no reason caused
by that should not be the case is they're fully backed by central bank money or short
duration, treasuries, then they should be, you know, generally acceptable and interchangeable.
Yes.
Again, better JP Morgan, assuming they have to abide by the same rules of having it fully
backed stable coin, no fractional reserves stable coin here, right, so they work on the
same terms as the amazon of this world or whoever else wants to issue stable coins.
No, I think you could see quite the law of stable coins depends on the magnitude of the
fixed costs of setting one up and making it operational for domestic and cross-border
transactions that I think these set up costs could be quite high, meaning that not too many
of them will arise, but that's the range to be seen.
Of course, the key here that the stable coins all be able to pay interest as well.
All right, so we need to take one more quick ad break and then we'll start to wrap up with
a couple of questions looking at it.
Finance is the world's number one crypto exchange, trusted by over 290 million users globally.
With world-class liquidity, security, and a wide portfolio of digital asset products,
finance makes crypto easy for everyone.
Whether you're new to crypto or a professional, finance offers a simple user experience.
Learn with Finance Academy, browse hundreds of tokens, and track your portfolio on an
easy-to-use dashboard.
For experienced users, Binance Pro provides industry-leading services and bespoke trading
products.
With some of the lowest fees and deepest liquidity in the market, it's no wonder over
290 million users choose Binance for everything crypto, buy, sell, trade, earn, live crypto.
Download Binance today and begin your journey into the future of finance.
Disclaimer, Binance is not available in certain countries, including the US, check its terms
for more information.
Binance.com/en/terms.
All right.
So we're back.
I want to ask you, there's a big FOMC meeting this week, it seems to be a virtual certainty
that there's going to be at least at 25.
Well, already done.
Yes.
Just a few places.
I'm curious, like, what are your expectations?
And I want to get your assessment of the economy, because there's a lot of different
opinions here.
I mean, for one, if you're looking at the employment market, maybe there are some concerns, but
overall, the economy seems healthy.
So there are those that say it doesn't make sense to be cutting into a strong economy.
What do you think?
It's most unfortunate that a number of other sector data on the real economy, the labor
market production, are delayed because of the government shutdown.
But inflation is still running at 3%, both headline and core, which is above target, unless
the Fed is surreptitiously changing the actual target to 3% behavior in the last year or two.
Do you think -- I don't mean to interrupt, but do you think 3% might be the new neutral
rate, or do you think we're -- I hope not, but I think it is a risk.
While I expect a Fed rate cut with 99% probability, I'm against it.
I don't think you should raise rates, unless there is evidence that a real economy, such
as the labor market, is weakening significantly.
And I haven't seen that evidence.
The U.S. Treasury has a triple mandate, as you know, maximum employment, stable price
prices, and moderate long-term interest rates, right?
And at the moment, I think long-term interest rates are moderate, inflation is above target,
and employment, as far as you can see, is still reasonably strong, although weakening.
So to me, the sensible course of action will be to wait even to raise the policy rate,
but it had a basis point.
The last cut was, I think, a mistake.
But this central bank must either have a different objective for inflation, or have a very different
view of the transmission mechanism or the policy, if they're going to cut as they will, now,
and no doubt in the next two meetings as well.
It's also -- I mean, it's hard to have this discussion and ignore just the immense amount
of pressure being put on a drone pal in the Fed from Trump and the White House.
I mean, he's talking about, like, two, three hundred percent cuts.
I mean, the Fed may have cut -- may have cut on its own last meeting, and it may have been
planned to do it again here, but, I mean, putting Stephen Moran on the FMC, the expectations
for who's going to replace pal next year, it certainly seems like, I guess, I think,
it's, like, sort of, like, the long tenet of an independent Fed.
I guess, ever since, like, Nixon, that might be a little bit tenuous at this point.
So I wonder how much that pressure -- I mean, it's probably hard to insulate yourself from
that type of pressure on being put on by the White House.
Well, then we'll find out soon whether the president can fire members of the board of
governors.
But when the courts rule on cooks the case, it's just allowed to stay on while there's
dispute of spending, clearly, if the president's interpretation of the president's ability
to fire board members for calls means that they can be fired for whatever reason the
president wants, then independence will be gone.
But Murund, I don't know how independent he is, but he kept his --
>> Yeah, you can't grab at the White House, well, Mark.
>> At the -- because of each of the advertisers, it's just the mental unpaid leave for five
or six months, I think, about -- just very bad visuals, because you don't want somebody
who has still got a job commitment with the federal government to be a board member.
But Powell, when he ends his term, a shared -- bill can stay, of course, as a member of
the board in '28, so that means that the new governor cannot be somebody appointed instead
of if Powell stays on, as I hope he will.
Of course, there will be -- so for the time being, Trump doesn't have a majority of appointees
among the seven governors, though, and of course, the 12 presidents of the regional reserve
banks, five of whom vote at any one time, cannot be sacked or appointed by the president.
And they have to be approved, in fact, and can be fired by the board.
So as long as Trump does not control the board, he doesn't control the FOMC.
Now, would the pressure be so severe that board members would cut wages, they think this
is not compatible with the mandate, I doubt it, I don't think we dare yet.
I just think that it's right is wrong, but not that there's lost their independence.
>> Okay.
Great.
Well, that's all I had.
Final thoughts, anything you'd like to say to wrap up our discussion?
>> No, I think that we have to not give up, despite the political position in Washington
and elsewhere on retail and wholesale center-bank digital currencies, on fully-backed stable
coins that pay interest and on enormous future, I see, for tokenized assets traded on the
blockchain, both domestically and cross-border.
We're going to have many more participants potentially in financial markets than they
had as a result of this decentralized finance world, but that creates new risks as well,
because some of the new investors will be deeply ignorant, and the tokenized assets are
just as risky as assets bought and sold clumsily using conventional means of payment.
But I do think that the web and the distributed ledges can really help to democratize finance.
>> All right.
Great.
Well, thank you so much for joining us.
We'll have to have you back.
>> Good luck.